[SPEAKER_01]: There's a short sutta that, um...
[SPEAKER_01]: It'll be interesting to hear your thoughts on.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the Udāna, chapter 7, the 8th sutta.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's about Kaccāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: So... On one occasion, the Buddha was living in Sarvati, in Jeta's wood, in Anathapindika's park.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, on that occasion, the Venerable Mahakacana was sitting not far from the Buddha, having crossed his legs, keeping his body upright, having properly set up recollectedness of the body internally.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, the word parimukkham, which... Around the mouth?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, internally means peripherally.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, having properly recollected the mind peripherally, the mind as the representative of the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're mindful of the entry points of your body, where the mind converges, you're mindful of the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because it's funny, because those two words, ājātaṅga and parimukhaṅga, are quite clearly adverbs.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're both together.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're both describing having set up, properly set up, mindfulness of the body in this way.
[SPEAKER_01]: ājātaṅga, parimukhaṅga.
[SPEAKER_01]: So ājātaṅga, so...
[SPEAKER_00]: The reason why it's peripheral is because it's not about attending to your mouth.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not about watching sensations on your lips or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not what mouth is, by the way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your mouth is not your lips.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, why would you be concentrating on your upper lip or whatever?
[SPEAKER_00]: People would do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sensations in your...
[SPEAKER_01]: Ask yourself, what is my mouth?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it has the physical aspect.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what is the significance of that physical aspect?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the whole thing, that's what mouth is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the physical side of it with the whole significance of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Consumption,
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, point of relationship with the world, pretty much a very personal thing, consumption internally, the speech, expression, communication, relation, everything converges on the mouth.
[SPEAKER_00]: You taking up the mouth in that manner, as in being ignorant of its nature, means you take up the entire body or bodily aspect of the mouth, which is what the body is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's almost like the the mouth is the
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, first point of contact, the...
[SPEAKER_00]: Pretty much, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's that, as I said before, it's a point of converging between, like, what's obviously mental and what's obviously physical.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, this is that in between where you are sort of muddled about.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, how can your thoughts enter your mouth?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, you are speaking your thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your mouth is...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how does that happen?
[SPEAKER_01]: Your mouth is almost more your thoughts than any other part of your body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's where the conceiving happens, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: You regard your mouth as internally, peripherally, as that which actually belongs to the mental.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it doesn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think also I'm right in saying that there's so much more muscular, like physical muscular control around the mouth than the other part of the body, the way we
[SPEAKER_00]: It is, it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: For animals, even more so.
[SPEAKER_00]: The entire existence revolves around the mouth.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you want to touch, communicate, do, everything is done with the mouth.
[SPEAKER_01]: More often than not.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's one way in which you can be mindful of the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, by peripherally...
[SPEAKER_01]: Discerning the image of the mouth.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, for you, while you're doing that, that
[SPEAKER_01]: Mouth stands for the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what it's meant in those, like, Ānāpānasati Sutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which says, whatever body there that he discerns through his recollectiveness of breathing, that's what the body is for him.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's one body in the bodies, within the bodies.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, that is what your body is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, by using that point... Well, it's not a point, but using, yeah, using the mouth as the body, to stand for the body...
[SPEAKER_01]: Using a phenomenon, I suppose.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: To stand for the body, you're choosing something like the most fundamental link between the mind and the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: What do you mean, you're choosing?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, why the mouth?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why the mouth?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, because the mouth just happens to be... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It has to be something.
[SPEAKER_01]: ...this most fundamental... Primal.
[SPEAKER_01]: ...primal connection, or not connection, but place where they do connect.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, through conceiving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like primal, but in a sense, natural way of sort of relating between the point of view and the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, because, as, you know, in the other suttas it said, the body paired with consciousness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Consciousness is not in the body, nor the body is in the consciousness.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just two simultaneous things.
[SPEAKER_00]: And their relationship results in the entire nāmarūpa, pretty much.
[SPEAKER_00]: That you can... anything you can perceive, feel, intend, is the result of consciousness paired with the body, or body and consciousness being there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that whole relationship between body and consciousness is inconceivable to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you were to conceive how is your body conscious, or how the consciousness has the body, that would imply that you can step outside of the... those aggregates and see how they relate.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's in... you are fully within it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the way this relationship is, of the five aggregates, is that, like mental and material, so to speak, superimposed together, and perception, feeling, intentions, they're all already points of converging, so to speak, action on account of mental in regard to physical, action on account of physical in regard to mental.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, now, if you look at it phenomenologically, there are going to be some points where these things converge.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Where the taking up of the body happens first.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, like, why is it a mouth?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's quite an irrelevant question.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, if it's not that, it would have been something else.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it probably revolves around the whole, you know, need for food, hunger, breastfeeding as a baby.
[SPEAKER_00]: The first, basically, point of pleasure, entrance into the world, is through your mouth.
[SPEAKER_00]: As a kid, as a toddler, you're completely unaware of your limbs and everything else, but you have awareness.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where your mind is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you kind of grow from there, but not at the expense of it, but through it.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, that framework of your mouth being the point of relationship with what remains.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can only... you can proliferate, infinitely so, within that framework.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, then, the growing becomes more...
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly, because it's the pleasure that governs the direction of your proliferation.
[SPEAKER_00]: If the mind is ignorant, which every mind is in the beginning, you go after pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, every point of pleasure will kind of create a channel for possible proliferation.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, your mouth being the main point, but then within that, you know, once... say you're not starving,
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't go hungry, you eat five times a day, you completely stop seeing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You stop seeing the point of pleasure being in your mouth and you start looking further.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's when the whole sexuality comes in, the groin.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why, literally, in that sutta where Ānanda was teaching to a nun, when he said it's the bridge, sexual intercourse is the destruction of the bridge.
[SPEAKER_00]: But see, compare it basically to the food.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to eat,
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can't stop eating.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the food for your point of contact of what the mouth is, is what the food is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the food for the point of contact of groin is sexual intercourse.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's the same thing, in a way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just one is proliferated further.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's the same principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, theoretically, you could understand that principle, but not before you actually stop providing food for the ground, literally.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what it said.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, no, this food is necessary, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, as a principle, the food is necessary to some extent, but not to the extent of sexual intercourse.
[SPEAKER_00]: That must be abandoned.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is absolutely no justification for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, you can't just stop eating food then, in order to undo the principle on the level of the mouth.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't stop having sexual intercourse, and you will undo the principle of depending on sexual pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can't do that to the food, because it's much more fundamental.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why, again, as we spoke in the Sutta, in the first jhāna, you can't speak, as in the speech has subsided, because you're not taking up the mouth to the point of actual possibilities of breaking into speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's when the first jhāna, sexuality or any sensuality, becomes inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're fully secluded from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you're not taking up your mouth in such manner, how can your mind proliferate further to the other parts of convergence of pleasure on account of body?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's right.
[SPEAKER_01]: So...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, this parimukhaṃ word, which is usually translated as just in front.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hmm.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's...
[SPEAKER_00]: I think it only appears in this stop phrase.
[SPEAKER_01]: With mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And...
[SPEAKER_01]: But it...
[SPEAKER_01]: But it is different types of mind, mindfulness and body, mindfulness of...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, it's the mindfulness, it's the recollectiveness of the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: But if we're to think of it as parimukkhangas, which is what it is literally, a pari around mukkhang mouth, around the mouth.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, that's why physical solitude was always, like, the Buddha would urge monks, because
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not communicating, there's no chit-chat, there's no speaking, there's no listening to the others.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because all those things imply convergent point of your mouth, of that whole domain of relationship, through verbal.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and although this, like, for example, most of these suttas don't talk about jhāna, although one of them does, I think.
[SPEAKER_01]: But most of them don't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, there is that one.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But...
[SPEAKER_01]: If this is to be understood as around the mouth, then it just... all this mindfulness is somehow much more closely related to jhāna than... Sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's how it's firstly related.
[SPEAKER_00]: Around the mouth means properly mindful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mindful proper representation of the phenomenon of the body in your experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can take that now in the direction of jhāna if you want.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you can then... Because it's on the basis of that same recollectedness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So just dwell on particular characteristics of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, you can take to the direction of brahma-vihāras, as that sutta says.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can take in many other directions, properly establish recollectedness of that which happens to be the point of convergence between your mind and your body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Usually, and again, like you see, if you were to start to think, like, what is, as we said before, what is speech?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it speech when you speak or when you don't speak?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it speech the sound that comes out of your mouth?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it's sort of... Is it speech?
[SPEAKER_00]: Your thoughts being sort of, you know, solidified into the verbal frequencies?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But how does that work?
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the air from my lungs that comes through the throat.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a geomechanical thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, my speech is the air from inside of me coming out and producing vibrations.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, are my thoughts in my belly?
[SPEAKER_00]: And then they somehow enter there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's ridiculous.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, by not thinking about it, you kind of merge it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You merge the two together, your thoughts and your speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: You cannot see how they're two simultaneous phenomena, but completely separate.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, they cannot possibly merge or relate.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just... And that's why, as Buddha said, having thought and pondered, as in having thinking and pondering there, enduring, one breaks into speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think it's funny how the...
[SPEAKER_01]: I think it's the philosophy... the tradition, the philosophers, I think since Thomas Aquinas, this idea of... to be human is to be that talking animal, the rational animal.
[SPEAKER_00]: Language is like really... Well, it's the domain of... yeah, of thought, of reflection, of expression, which is kind of limited to... well, certainly doesn't go lower than the humans.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, other animals might be able to communicate, yeah, through sound, but it's far from establishing a domain of, yeah, of speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just significance.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, our whole... what we are is based on this idea of this connection between the the mind and the mental via language, via the mouth, via the speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind and the material.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind and the material, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's same with the food, again.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you know, you think, like, by consuming food, by disappearing in you, you think, like, it's in you.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the food is in the belly, which is out there with this table and this pot and the food.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the food is still closer to where it was before, than it's inside of me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, the whole notion of consumption is, like, literally, you are that barrier through which passes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now it's in you, but... oh, wait, there is no in me.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just a point of view in regard to this whole thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And all that in, it's peripheral to, from what, in regard to what you're looking for.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it's ājātā, the Pāli internal.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Literally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ājātā, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: In terms of significance, it's literally what, what, what peripheral is.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the more you develop it, the less mind it sees, it continues to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, maybe we can say, having crossed his legs, this is Mahakacana sitting there, having crossed his legs, keeping his body upright, having properly set up recollectiveness of the body, peripherally around the mouth.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the Buddha sees this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Having seen the meaning of this, on that occasion, he uttered this utterance.
[SPEAKER_01]: For whoever... and it's a verse... for whoever there is always recollectedness, constantly established on the body...
[SPEAKER_00]: The verse is inspired by what he described.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when he says mindfulness, recollectiveness means basically recognizing the image of the body peripherally, not actually attending to what you're perceiving, which is the result of the body being there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your perception of your own body is secondary.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's always and constantly, always, always... For whoever there is, always recollectedness constantly establishes on the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: That doesn't mean focusing on something...
[SPEAKER_00]: Body, body, body, body.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means, like, recollectedness, the context is always there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anything that occurs is within it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And full discernment of that makes the context imperturbable.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's always constantly there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then he says this... Because the body is always constantly there, by the way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether you...
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether you want it or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether you're aware of that or not, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then he says, it could not be.
[SPEAKER_01]: It could not be mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will not be.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will not be mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: He who regularly stays in that place,
[SPEAKER_01]: At the right time, he crosses over attachments.
[SPEAKER_00]: This shows all the conceit, sense of I am.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, as we just said, when we started this, that mindfulness of peripherally, the mouth is the convergence point, that's not speaking, is mindfulness of the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you train in that kind of peripheral image, peripheral recognition, recollectedness, you become familiar with the nature of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the nature of the body is there, like a like a lump.
[SPEAKER_00]: Collection, like pile of elements, like other things that are around here, that are clearly not yours, clearly cannot be yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the point of that that cryptic verse.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not cryptic at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means like, not just that it's not mine, but even in the future, things cannot be any different, so that things could possibly become mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, not just that it could not be for me, it won't be for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either way, it cannot be for me in the future, because
[SPEAKER_00]: It's all on the basis of this right now, which is unownable.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I mean, basically, it could not be.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means like, okay, so there's this thing here, but it could not be.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: First, you have no saying the thing that's here.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it could have not been.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You could say that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You could translate it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It could have not been here, but whatever it is, it won't be mine or for me because, again, it came on its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's nothing other than like full development of the principle that already Sotāpanna understands.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever is of the nature to arise, that's why it's of nature to cease.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's nothing... it's not like cryptic.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like some Vedic old verse or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just a description of anicca.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: On a most accurate level.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there is absolutely not even the slightest room for the sense of I am to remain lingering in regards to that which could have not been, which means you're not saying it's arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, and if it could have... if it, like, it could not have been manifested, in which case, there's no possibility for it to be mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that possibility for it to be mine is not meant to be me.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just happens to be... because that... it becomes possible because that thing happens to have manifested.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, which means...
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter how much of it...
[SPEAKER_01]: It depends upon something which I have no control over.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it doesn't matter how much of it it is felt as mine, how much of it it is mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fundamentally, it cannot be mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there is no mind without thing given beforehand.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is now mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that whole verse, it's not like a description of a process of what happens or how you have to reason.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just a direct insight of whatever is of the nature to arise.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not because I wait for it to see it disappear or because I apply myself.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's because it has a reason on its own.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it will have
[SPEAKER_00]: It's input.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why I cannot own it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Full stop.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's be explicit.
[SPEAKER_01]: It, here, means the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: As we talked about, this is mindfulness of the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: And mindfulness of the, like, recollectiveness of the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Body being the necessary basis for everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your whole universe, as I would say, is within the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Within the basis of that body.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you regard the body as that which is just
[SPEAKER_00]: Could have not been, as in, I'm not saying it's a rising which means I'm not, I'm not its master, which means there is, I cannot entertain ownership even if I want to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's automatically felt, by the way, the absence of ownership.
[SPEAKER_00]: Once you see it correctly, you don't need to then go and let go of your ownership on account of what you understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your understanding means letting go of the ownership.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that also will start to pertain that to the possibility of the future body, as in later on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, see, if you're not completely free from doubt, like, it might be apparent that now nothing can be yours, but there is a still tacit assumption that things might be different in the future, to some extent, and to that extent, to allow you to own them.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now, even the whole domain, not the particular possibility of this or that, but the domain of the possibility, as in the nature of possibilities,
[SPEAKER_00]: It has to be of the same nature that it's unownable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's... it could have not been.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, it won't be for me, whichever way it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Cannot be for me, even if I wanted to.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's irregularly staying in that place.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Clarifying
[SPEAKER_00]: Recollecting and then clarifying what you recollected, the context of the body correctly, which is that peripheral
[SPEAKER_00]: Recognition that the body is here.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, I'm talking to you, feeling like this, thinking that, want to do that, because this body is here, enduring as a necessary basis for all these possibilities and actual engagements.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not about you finding in, like, the particular points of your body sensations and attending to it, because I see that, in order to do that, you need to ignore the context.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, that's another act you're caught up in.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm attending this, I'm attending this, I'm feeling, touching, moving, moving, whatever else.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of that is possible because the body is there beforehand already.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's where your mindfulness is.
[SPEAKER_00]: On recollecting that right order, recollecting that correct image, the mind comes first, because the right image comes first.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's that's the entire point.
[SPEAKER_00]: The clearer that becomes,
[SPEAKER_00]: The harder to lose it, it will become.
[SPEAKER_00]: The harder to distract yourself from it, it will become.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that means you're going to be... your experience will be more and more and more dispassionate.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And at the right time, he crosses over attachments.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in all... all of the... all of the conceits, all the attachments, all the senses of ownership, or whatever else you've been sort of entertaining, however vaguely,
[SPEAKER_00]: It ceased.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you stopped providing a fertile basis for it.